Guide to the Alabados (religious songs) and folk and nativity plays of Mexico, New Mexico, Colorado and Colombia, 1869-1949
Department of Special Collections
Alabados (religious songs) and folk and nativity plays of Mexico, New Mexico, Colorado and Colombia,
1869-1949
Special Collections M0141
Rael, Juan B., collector.
3.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Juan B. Rael, 1966.
Scope and Content
Folk plays of Mexico, New Mexico, Colorado and Columbia on religious subjects. Also, alabades, or religious songs. See Contents List.
Container List
- 1. Typescript of a Shepherds' Nativity play, entitled Una Pastorela. Una Caminata a Belén was secured from Francisco Pichardo of Taxco Mexico. For a discussion of it and a summary of the plot see Rael's The Sources and the Diffusion of the Mexican Shepherds' Plays, pp. 256 - 259 (hereinafter cited as Rael's). (Box 1)
- 2. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherd's play, entitled Pastorela, was secured from Encaración Rivas of Zapopan, a suburb of Guadalajara, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 292 - 294. (Box 1)
- 3. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherds' play, entitled Coloquio de pastores, was obtained from a native of Uruapan, Michoacan, Mexico. According to him, he brought it to Uruapan from Coitiaj de la Paz in the state of Micoacan. See Rael's, pp. 287 - 290. (Box 1)
- 4. Manuscript of a play dealing with the finding of Our Lord at the Temple, entitled Comedia del Niño Perdido, was secured from Onécimo Martínez of Ensenada (near Tierra Amarilla), New Mexico. (Box 1)
- 5. Manuscript of a play dealing with the finding of Our Lord at the Temple, entitled Auto del Nino Perdido, was secured from Juan Tenorio of Taos, New Mexico. Formerly it belonged to Julian M. Tenorio. (Box 1)
- 6. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherds' play, entitled Coloquir de pastores, was obtained from Encarnación Rivas of Zapopan, a suburb of Guadalajara, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 297 - 299. (Box 1)
- 7. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherds' play, entitled Cuaderno dedicado al Nino Dios en Belén en su Nacimiento, was obtained from Manuel Nolasco of Uruapan, Michoacan, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 290 - 292. (Box 1)
- 8. Typescript, entitled Pastorela, was obtained from Luis Figueroa of Jiquilpan, Michoacan, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 285 - 287. (Box 1)
- 9. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherds' play, entitled Coloquio de las sinco letras, was secured from Encarnación Rivas of Zapepan, Jalisco, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 295 - 297. (Box 1)
- 10. Manuscript of a play of the Magi, entitled La Adoración de los Reyes cuando estos llegaron al pesebre, was obtained from Pedro A. Víez R. of Itaguí, a suburb of Medellín, Colombia, in 1953.For discussion of the play see Michael Doudoroff's dissertation at Stanford University entitled The Story of the Magi in Spanish Literature and Folklore. (Hereinafter cited as Doudoroff). (Box 1)
- 11. Manuscript of a play of the Magi, entitled Colquios misticos del dis de los Reyes, was obtained from Pedro A. Vélez R. of Itaguí, a suburb of Medellín, Colombia, in 1953.For many years, Senor Vélez directed the play and was one of the actors in it. See Dourdoroff's dissertation. (Box 1)
- 12. This manuscript book was obtained from Juan Tenorio of Taos, New Mexico. It contains the following materials: (Box 1)
  La Prime (primera) Demarcación (Persecusión) de Jesús, a play of the Magi discussed by Michael Doudoroff in his dissertation.
  A shepherds' play entitled Aucto pastoral. See Rael's, pp. 74 - 83.
  A number of labados or religious songs used by the penitentes of New Mexico. See Rael's The New Mexican `Alabado.'
- 13. Manuscript of a play of the Magi, was obtained from José Inés Arellano of Arroyo Hondo. New Mexico. He had copied it from a Ranchitos de taos manuscript. See Doudoroff's dissertation. (Box 1)
- 14. Manuscript, entitled Comedia de los Reyes Magos, [a play of the Magi], was obtained from Onésimo de Jesús Martinez of Ensenada, New Mexico. See Doudoroff's. (Box 1)
- 15. Manuscript book of alabados, religious songs used by the flagellant brothers or penitentes of New Mexico and southern Colorado, was secured from Francisco Jaramillo of Alamosa, Colorado. See Rael's The New Mexican `Alabado.' (Box 1)
- 16. Manuscript of a New Mexican folk play entitled Comedia del Niño Perdido, and deals with the finding of Our Lord in the Temple. It was obtained from Onésimo Martinez of Tierra Amarilla, New Mexico, but formerly of Albiquiú, New Mexico. Besides the play, the manuscript book contains entries of births and list of contriubutions collected. The book also contains an alabado or religious song used at wakes dealing with the preparation of the Virgin of Guadalupe to Inian Juan Diego. It also contains religious songs in honor of San Ramon and San Isidro. (Box 1)
- 17. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherds' play, entitled Los Siete Vicios, was obtained from Rómulo Gaitán. Formerly it had belonged to Ramón and Trinidad Luna. See Rael's, pp. 136 - 140. (Box 1)
- 18. This manuscript contains the Mexican folk play entitled Moros y Cristianos. It is a play dramatizing a battle between Moors and Christians and is generally staged during feast day of St. John the Baptist at the little village of Guadalupe, Zaxatecas, Mexico. The stage for the play is the large field in which the two armies meet. The manuscript was secured from Predro Nayar of Guadalupe, Zaxatecas. (Box 1)
- 19. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherds' play, entitled Cuaderno de Pastores, was obtained from Dolores Reyna of Saltillo, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 161 - 176. (Box 2)
- 20. Manuscript of a Nativity Shepherds' play, entitled Cuaderno de Pastorela para uso de la Sra. Maria Antuna, was obtained with the help of Francisco González of Durango, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 66 - 69. (Box 2)
- 21. Manuscript of a Mexican Shepherds' play, entitled Cuaderno de pastores dedicado al Nacimiento de Cristo, used to belong to Jesús Fernando Ramírez of Durango, Mexico, and was secured with the help of Francisco Gonzalez. However, it reached the collector too late to be included in his Sources and Diffusion. A brief examination of the manuscript reveals that it is a version of Text I, discussed in pp. 54 - 114. (Box 2)
- 22. Manuscript of a Nativity shepherds' play, entitled Pastorela de los siete vicios o sea el Nacimiento del Niño Dios, was obtained from Donaciano Guevara of Aguascalientes, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 152 - 160. (Box 2)
- 23. This manuscript, entitled Cuaderno para Pastorela, was obtained with the help of Francisco González from Francisco Cervantes of Durango, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 70 - 74. (Box 2)
- 24. This manuscript is of a Mexican Nativity shepherds' play, entitled Cuaderno de Pastorela. It was secured from the Primitivo Corra of Monterrey, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 166 - 171. (Box 2)
- 25. Manuscript of a play dealing with the first fall of man, entitled Coloqui de Adán y Eva, was secured from José María Burciaga of Durango, Mexico. (Box 2)
- 26. Manuscript of a play dealing with the story of the Good Thief, entitled Coloqui en Honor del Benturoso Ladrón, San Dimas, was secured from Luciano Pichardo of Taxco, Mexico. The original owner of the manuscript was Casimior Osorio. (Box 2)
- 27. Manuscript of a play dealing with the finding of Our Lord at the Temple, entitled Auto de Jesús Niño Perdido, was secured from José Ezequiel Arellan of Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. The manuscript was copied from an older manuscript belonging to Ricardo Archuleta of Cerro, New Mexico. (Box 3)
- 28. The typescript contained in this envelope is entitled La Adoración de los Santos Reyes or El Nacimiento del Niño Jesús. This is a play dealing with the story of the Magi. Doudoroff discusses this drama in his Ph.D. dissertation. The typescript was secured from Enrique Sáchez of Oaxaxa, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 254 - 256. (Box 3)
- 29. Manuscript of a folk play written to celebrate the feast of the Holy Cross entitled Cuaderno de la Santísima Cruz, originally belonged to Benito Galindo. The manuscript was obtained for the collector with the help of Francisco González of Durango, Mexico. (Box 3)
- 30. Manuscript of shepherds' play entitled Pastorela obtained from Juan de Dios Vega of Tehuantepec, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 248 - 250. (Box 3)
- 31. Typescript of a folk play on the apparition of the Virgin of Guadalupe to Indian, Juan Diego. It was obtained from Francisco González of Durango, Mexico in 1962. (Box 3)
- 32. This manuscript book contains two folk plays. The first one is a shepherds' play entitled Cuaderno de pastores dedicado al Niño Dios. See Rael's, pp. 64 - 66. The second play is entitled Coloquio de Adan and deels with Adán and Eve in Paradise. The manuscript was obtained from Benito Cavada. (Box 3)
- 33. Manuscript of a Nativity shepherds' play entitled La noche más venturosa El premio de la inocencia. It was obtained from Luciano Pichard of Taxco, Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 196 - 198. (Box 3)
- 34. This manuscript book of alabados, religious songs used by the penitentes of New Mexico and southern Colorado was obtained from Esteban Sanchez of Antonito, Colorado. For a discussion of the alabados, see Rael's The New Mexican Alabado. (Box 3)
- 35. Manuscript book of a folk play dealing with the Finding of Our Lord at the Temple, secured from José Inés Arellano of Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. (Box 3)
- 36. Manuscript book of a play dealing with the Finding of Our Lord at the Temple, obtained from José Horacio Garcia of Alamosa, Colorado. (Box 3)
- 37. Manuscript book of a play dealing with the Finding of Our Lord at the Temple, obtained from Pedro Aranda of Santa Cruz, New Mexico. (Box 3)
- 38. Manuscript of a play dealing with the Finding of Our Lord at the Temple, secured from Ricardo Archuleta of Cerro, New Mexico. (Box 4)
- 39. Manuscript containing a Nativity shepherds' play, secured from Alfredo Romero of Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. See Rael's, p. 88. (Box 4)
- 40. Manuscript of a Nativity shepherds' play, secured from Onécimo Martinez of Tierra Amarilla. See Rael's, p. 90. (Box 4)
- 41. This manuscript book, obtained from Ricardo Archuleta of Cerro, New Mexico, contains the following: (Box 4)
  A Version of a shepherds' Nativity play. See Rael's, pp. 83 - 84.
  A dramatization of the search for lodging by St. Joseph and Mary (Las Posadas).
  A number of alabados. See Rael's The New Mexican Alabado.
- 42. Manuscript book containing a version of a Nativity shepherds' play, obtained from Manuel de Atocha Arellano of Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. See Rael's, p. 86. (Box 4)
- 43. Manuscript book containing a Nativity shepherds' play, obtained from José Inés Arellano of Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. See Rael's, p. 87. (Box 4)
- 44. Manuscript book containing a Nativity shepherds' play, secured from Remigio Martines of Antonito, Colorado. See Rael's, p. 95. (Box 4)
- 45. Manuscript of a Nativity shepherds' play, obtained from Geronimo Quintan of Guadalupe, Colorado. See Rael's, p. 96. (Box 4)
- 46. This manuscript book contains three items. (Box 4)
  Several alabados or religious songs used by the penitentes.
  Las Posadas, a dramatization of the search for lodging by Joseph and Mary.
  A version of Nativity shepherds' play. See Rael's, p. 91.
  The book was obtained from the widow of Horacio García of Alamosa, Colorado.
- 47. Manuscript book, containing a Nativity shepherds' play, obtained from Florencio Martinez of Valdés, New Mexico. See Rael's, pp. 13 - 14. (Box 4)
  FOR INFORMATION ABOUT ITEMS 48 - 64, SEE RAEL'S The New Mexican Alabado.
- 48. Manuscript book of alabados, religious songs used by the penitentes of New Mexico and Colorado (southern), obtained from Felix Pino of Santa Fe, New Mexico. (Box 4)
- 49. Manuscript book of alabados, religious songs used by the penitentes of New Mexico and southern Colorado, secured from Remigio Martinez of Conejos, Colorado. (Box 4)
- 50. Manuscript book of alabados,... secured from Justo López of Española, New Mexico. (Box 4)
- 51. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Alfonso Chàvez of Los Cerritos, Colorado. (Box 4)
- 52. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Justo Lopez of López, New Mexico. (Box 4)
- 53. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Justo López. (Box 4)
- 54. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Justo López. (Box 5)
- 55. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Justo López. (Box 5)
- 56. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Esteban Medina of Alamosa, Colorado. (Box 5)
- 57. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Alfredo Romero of Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. (Box 5)
- 58. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Luis Montoya of Cerro, New Mexico. (Box 5)
- 59. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Ricardo Archuleta of Cerro, New Mexico. (Box 5)
- 60. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Blas Montoya of Espinoca, Colorado. (Box 5)
- 61. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Jose I. Arellano of Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. (Box 5)
- 62. Manuscript book of alabados,... from J. M. Armenta of Conejos, Colorado. (Box 5)
- 63. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Moises Gutierrez of Antonito, Colorado. (Box 5)
- 64. Manuscript book of alabados,... from Justo López of Espanola, New Mexico. (Box 5)
- 65. This manuscript book contains the play of the Magi. The manuscript is entitled Coloqui que le llaman de los Reyes. It originally belonged to Agustín Palafox, the copyist, of Pánuco, Zacatecas, Mexico. The collector secured the manuscript of Ignacio Torres Vasquez of San Luis Potosi, Mexico. See Doudoroff. (Box 6)
- 66. Manuscript of a Nativity shepherds' play entitled Coloqui en Honor de Señor San José, obtained with the help of Francisco Gonzalez of Durango, Mexico. It belonged originally to J. Fernando Ramírez of the same city. The manuscript reached the collector too late to be included in his Sources and Diffusion. An examination of the manuscript reveals, however, that it is a version of Text VIII, see Rael's, pp. 177 - 190. (Box 6)
- 67. Manuscript of a Nativity shepherds' play entitled En al tiemp mas soberano en los campos de Belén, obtained from Omagón Trejo of Zapopan, Jalisco, Mexico. For a brief summary of the plot see Rael's, pp. 229 - 302. (Box 6)
- 68. Manuscript book, obtained from Rómulo Gaitán of Guadalupe, Zacatecas, Mexico, contains two Nativity shepherds' plays. The first one is entitled Pastorela de los Siete Vicios. See Rael's, pp. 133- 135. The second play, Pastorela, is discussed on pp. 55 - 63. (Box 6)
- 69. This manuscript book contains two Mexican folk plays. The first one is a Nativity shepherds' play entitled Cuaderno de pastores. The manuscript reached the collector too late to be included in his book... An examination of the play, however, reveals that this is another Durange version of Text I, see pp. 54 - 114. The second play is a folk play entitled Coloquio de Nuestra Señora del Refugio. This is another mystery play with many allegorical characters. The manuscript book was obtained with the help of Francisco González of Durango, Mexico. The book does not bear the original owner's name. (Box 6)
- 70. Manuscript of a Nativity shepherds' play entitled Coloquio de Senor San José y de Mariá Santiima, obtained from Rómulo Gaitán of Guadalupe, Zacatecas, Mexico. See Rael, pp. 176 - 186. (Box 6)
- 71. Manuscript of a Mexican folk play, entitled Cuaderno del Coloquio de adoración de los Santos Reves Magos del Oriente al Niño Dios en al Portal de Belén cuando está recién nacido. This deals with biblical story of The Magi, secured from Omagón Trejo of Zapopan, Jalisco, Mexico. See Doudoroff. (Box 7)
- 72. Manuscript of Mexican play, story of The Magi, no title, secured from Rómulo Gaitán of Guadalupe, Zacatecas, Mexico. See Doudoroff. (Box 7)
- 73. Manuscript of book containing folk play dealing with the apparition of Virgin of Guadalupe to Juan Diego, obtained in Durango, Mexico in 1963from Francisco González who had bought it from José Romero, original owner, of Durango. (Box 7)
- 74. Manuscript book containing a Nativity Shepherds' play entitled Proceso de adoración del Santo Niño, obtained from Alberto Aquino of Juchitán, Tehuantepec, Mexico. See Rael, pp. 251 - 256. (Box 7)
- 75. Manuscript book containing a shepherds' play entitled Coloquio y Pastores de los Siete Vicios, secured from Rómulo Gaitán of Guadalupe, Zacatecas, Mexico. See Rael, pp. 127 - 133. (Oversize OS)
- 76. Manuscript of a shepherds' play of the Nativity of Christ, entitled Cuaderno de adoración, obtained from Ignacio Torres Vazquez of San Luis Potosi, Mexico, over 8,000 lines. See Rael, pp. 302 - 305. (Oversize OS)
- Rael Microfilm
  - 1. Huntington Library microfilm strip. Coloquio de los Pastores. Uncatalogued from the Aguilar Papers. Dec. 30, 1861., 56 pp.
  - 2. A. Autos sacramentales, y al nacimiento de Christo, con sus loas, y entremeses. Recogidos de los maiores uigenios de Espana. Dedicados a Don Diego Perez Orejon (Oregon), Secretario del Rey neustro Senio, y Escriuano Mayor de Ayuntamiento de esta Coronada Villa de Madrid. Con Licencia,... En Madrid: Por Antonio Francisco de Zafra. Ano de 1675.351 - 360 duplicated on a strip. D 152.12., 390 pp.
    Boston Public Library
  - 2. B. Autos Sacramentales Con Quatro Comedias Nue Vas, y sus Loas, y Entremesses Primera Parte Dedicado Don Francisco de Camargo, Cauallero de la Order de Santiago. No p. 112, 153, 150. Dup. p. 177, 176. D 175.13., 357 pp.
  - 3. Archivo Nacional Guatemala. 17 Manuscript Loas & Entremes., Reel I.
  - 4. Archivo Nacional Guatemala. ca. 30 Manuscript Leas, etc., Reel II.
    In microfilm drawer